Pamela Moore papers 13202800
Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Pamela Moore Papers
1939-2018
1950-1964
Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Moore, Pamela, 1937-1964
13202800
MS#1928
12.75 linear feet 21 document boxes, 1 record storage carton, 1 card file box, 6 custom book boxes, and 1 temporary box
Pamela Moore (1937-1964) was an American novelist, best known for Chocolates for Breakfast (1956). The papers contain correspondence, clippings, contracts, diaries, drafts, manuscripts, memorabilia, photographs, notebooks, notes, outlines, proofs, school materials, sketch books, and a collection of published editions of Moore's novels.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in seven series and several subseries.
Restrictions on Access
This collection is located on-site.
Restrictions on Access
Digital files can be accessed upon request via a secure laptop in the Rare Book & Manuscript Library's Reading Room. Otherwise, this collection has no restrictions.
Restrictions on Access
Some materials currently housed in a temporary boxes will be reboxed, but all items are accessible at this time. Please note that the final diary has a very fragile binding and should be handled with care.
Summary
Pamela Moore (1937-1964) was an American novelist, best known for Chocolates for Breakfast (1956). Although Moore's career was short, the collection contains a wealth of documentation about her life and writings during this period. The papers contain correspondence, clippings, contracts, diaries, drafts, manuscripts, memorabilia, photographs, notebooks, notes, outlines, proofs, school materials, sketch books, and a collection of published editions of Moore's novels.
Summary
The collection also includes materials related to Moore's unpublished works, including articles, novels, short stories, plays, and poetry. The collection contains a significant amount of materials for both Prophets Without Honor and Kathy, including contracts, notes, notebooks, outlines, typescripts, and other materials. These are also working files for several other projects that include character sketches, notes, synopses, and manuscripts of varying lengths. There are also typescripts for poems and several short stories, and some materials related to ideas for plays. The collection includes notes, typescripts for both published and unpublished articles, as well as copies of Moore's published articles. In many cases, Moore's unpublished works are untitled, so some manuscripts may be found to be related to one another or to larger novel projects upon further examination of the available records.
Summary
The collection includes contracts, outlines, typescripts, setting copies, and other materials related to Moore's published novels. The collection lacks a full typescript for render"italic">The Exile of Suzy Q, but includes working files with typescript pages. For Chocolates for Breakfast and The Pigeons of St. Marks / East Side Story / Diana, which went through some revisions, there are multiple typescripts and revisions in the collection. There are several published editions of all of Moore's novels in the collection, as well, primarily of foreign editions of her works.
Summary
The collection also includes material related to Moore's professional activities, including correspondence, contracts, clippings files, financial records, photographs, and memorabilia.
Summary
Moore's papers contain many personal materials, including books, correspondence, diaries, financial records, a passport, photographs, receipts, school records, sketchbooks, and travel notes. These records shed light on Moore's relationships with her husband, her family, and with Edouard de Laurot, among others. Later correspondence and notes by others also shed light on Moore's life and work. Lastly, Moore's diaries provide insight into her family life, emotional life, relationships, social life, travel, writings, and ultimately, in her final diary entries, her suicide.
Summary
The collection includes printed materials related to Moore's life and work. There are several editions of Moore's published novels; these are primarily foreign editions. The editions include original editions of Moore's novels, as well as foreign editions based upon the Harper Perennial edition of Chocolates for Breakfast (2013). The printed materials also include several books owned by Moore, several of which are inscribed to her, or signed by her. A few of these also relate to equestrians who knew and worked with Moore.
Summary
A copy of the catalog prepared the literacy agency for this collection is included with the papers. The catalog provides more detailed subject information and context on correspondence, diaries, manuscripts, and other materials in the collection. While the final arrangement and organization of the collection differs from the catalog, it is still a valuable resource.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
2017.2018.M104: Source of acquisition--Kevin Kanarek (Represented by Sarah Funke-Butler). Method of acquisition--Purchase; Date of acquisition--2018.
Biographical / Historical
Pamela Moore was born on September 22, 1937, the daughter of Donald and Isabel Moore (née Walsh). Both of Moore's parents were writers. They had married in 1934, and Isabel's young daughter, Elaine, had adopted Moore's surname after their marriage. By the mid-1940s, the Moores had divorced, and Pamela Moore split time between her father in California and her mother in New York.
Biographical / Historical
While studying at Barnard College, Moore published her first book Chocolates for Breakfast in 1956. The first American edition of the book was published in September 1956, at the start of Moore's senior year. As Moore had planned to spend her senior year in France, she had already left the county when the edition was published in the United States. The novel became a bestseller not only in the United States, but also in Italy and France. The book went into multiple printings and was translated into several languages. The book gained notoriety for its content, which was uncommon for the 1950s, and it was compared to Bonjour Tristesse by Françoise Sagan at the time. Moore spent much of the next two years in Europe, returning to the United States in the spring of 1958.
Biographical / Historical
Moore was educated at Rosemary Hall (now Choate Rosemary Hall) and Barnard College. While Moore was matriculated with the Class of 1957 at Barnard College, it appears that she received her diploma in 1958 from the records in the collection.
Biographical / Historical
Moore married Adam Kanarek shortly after returning to the United States in 1958. The couple settled in New York, where Kanarek was studying at Brooklyn Law School. They had one son, Kevin, in 1963.
Biographical / Historical
Moore wrote another novel during this period, Prophets Without Honor, but it remains unpublished. Moore had started this novel in Europe, and it was based upon her relationship with Edouard de Laurot, whom she had met on her way to France in 1956. Knopf had bought the novel based upon an outline, but rejected the finished manuscript when it diverged significantly from the original outline and ultimately rescinded its contract.
Biographical / Historical
Moore published three additional novels after Chocolates for Breakfast but none of these matched the success of her first novel. Moore's next novel was rejected by American publishers, and published as Les Pigeons de Saint Marc by Julliard in France (1960) and as East Side Story by Longmans (1961). The book received favorable reviews in France and was reviewed in the Times Literary Supplement in the United Kingdom, but it did not receive much notice otherwise. The development of a screenplay for Chocolates for Breakfast was also explored during this period, but ultimately the project did not move forward. Moore's next novel, L'Exil de Suzy-Cœur, was published only in France (1962), and Moore and Kanarek travelled to Europe for its publication. Moore's last novel, The Horsy Set, was published by Simon & Schuster in 1963, but it did not sell well, and did not receive reviews in prominent magazines or literary publications.
Biographical / Historical
Moore continued to write, and began work on a novel tentatively titled Kathy, which had grown out of her revisions to Prophets Without Honor. The novel remained unfinished at the time of Moore's death.
Biographical / Historical
Moore died by suicide on June 7, 1964, at her home in New York City.
Accruals
No additional material is expected.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. Contact rbml@columbia.edu for more information.
Novelists; Fiction (general genre); Diaries; Correspondence; Personal papers; Clippings (Information Artifacts); Manuscripts (documents); Photographs; Sketchbooks; Moore, Pamela, 1937-1964; Lord, Sterling, 1920-; McCall, Monica; Moore, Don, 1904-1986; Moore, Isabel, 1911-1989; Barnard College; Simon and Schuster, Inc; Julliard (Firm); Longmans, Green, and Co.; Alfred A. Knopf, Inc.
- Series I: Manuscripts and Related Materials, 1942-2013 [Bulk Dates: 1950-1964]
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes manuscripts as well as related materials such as drafts, notes, notebooks, outlines, and proofs.
  Contracts for first editions were originally filed with the corresponding manuscripts, and are included in this series. Additional contracts are filed in Subseries II.2: Contracts.
  In general, any related correspondence is filed in the professional correspondence files in Subseries II.1.
  - Subseries I.1: Published Novels, circa 1952-1964, 2013
    This subseries contains contracts, drafts, manuscripts, outlines, and proofs for Moore's four published novels.
    - Subseries I.1.1: Chocolates for Breakfast, circa 1952-1956, 2013
      The first American edition of Chocolates for Breakfast was published by Rinehart in September 1956, with the French edition being published by Julliard soon after, in November. A second French edition, the "nouvelle édition" that included new revisions by the author, was published in 1957.
      This subseries includes a contract, drafts, excerpts, typescripts, and the setting copy for the first American edition. There is also a file of working material for the Nouvelle Edition, which came to the collection from Eddie de Laurot, the son of Edouard de Laurot. In addition, there are proofs and related correspondence for the Harper Perennial Edition, published in 2013.
      There are some early short stories related to Chocolates for Breakfast in Subseries I.3: Short Stories.
      - 1st Edition--Contract (Rinehart & Company), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - 1st Edition--Turning Point (Story 1) and Untitled (Story 2), 1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Note on pencil (not by Moore) associates the character of Bill in this story with the character of Barry in the novel.
      - 1st Edition--Typescript (Incomplete), circa 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Pages 2-283.
      - 1st Edition--Ribbon Typescript, circa 1956; 2 folders (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
        The original clean version of the typescript carbon that became the setting copy.
      - 1st Edition--Setting Copy, circa 1956; 2 folders (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
        Annotated, with substantial corrections. Pages that were cut are included in the setting copy, with pencil lines through the pages.
      - 1st Edition--Excerpt, circa 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Pages 117-122.
      - Nouvelle Edition (French), circa 1956; 2 folders (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
        This contains about 2" of working material, primarily of inserts and the preface. Substantial annotations. In English and in French.
      - Harper Perennial Edition--Proofs and Related Correspondence (Folders 1-5, of 8), 2013; 5 folders (Box 2, Folder 3-7)
        Several sets of proofs, with some related cover letters, for the reissue of Chocolates for Breakfast in 2013.
      - Harper Perennial Edition--Proofs and Related Correspondence (Folders 6-8, of 8), 2013; 3 folders (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - Subseries I.1.2: The Pigeons of St. Marks / East Side Story / Diana, circa 1959-1963
      The working title for this novel was The Pigeons of St. Marks and it was published as Les Pigeons de Saint Marc by Julliard (1960). It was published as East Side Story by Longmans in the United Kingdom (1961) and later as Diana by Dell in the United States (1964). The Dell contract (1963) is included in this subseries.
      The subseries includes an outline, sample copy, and the setting copy and the long galleys for the Longmans version. The revised manuscripts were possibly circulated to American publishers, such as Fawcett.
      - East Side Story--Contract (Dell), 1963 December (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Pigeons of St. Marks--Outline, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 5)
        Outline, with 2 pages typescript notes reviewing the outline, and 4 pages of handwritten notes following the outline.
      - Pigeons of St. Marks--Sample Copy, 1960; 2 folders (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
        Wrapper notes that this is the "1st copy of original Pigeons manuscript. No edition was made from this." 244 pp. ribbon typescript on onion skin, largely stamped by Odette Arnaud, and "Exemplaire de Press / Sample Copy."
      - East Side Story--Setting Copy (Longmans), circa 1961; 2 folders (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
        Wrapper notes that this is a "Copy of Pigeons manuscript original version from which the Brisith edition was set. 244 pages"
      - East Side Story--Long Galleys, circa 1961 (Box 22, Folder 1)
        "Marked Proof" with proof reader marks in blue ink.
      - Pigeons of St. Marks--Revised, circa 1962 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Pigeons of St. Marks--Revised Copy for Fawcett, 1962; 2 folders (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
        With envelope.
      - Pigeons of St. Marks--Typescript Carbon, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
        Pages 298-307 (Chapter 17) only.
    - Subseries I.1.3: The Exile of Suzy Q, 1961-1964
      This subseries includes the contracts with Julliard (1961) and Paperback Library (1963), as well as a cover proof, and a file with various typescript pages, corrections, and drawings of maps. The collection does not include a full typescript or proof for this book.
      There is related material in Subseries I.7: Drafts and Fragments.
      - Contract (Julliard), 1961 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Contract (Paperback Library), 1963 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Cover Proof (Paperback Library), circa 1964 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Various typescript pages, corrections, and drawings of maps, 1961, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Subseries I.1.4: The Horsy Set, 1962-1963
      This subseries includes the contract and setting copy, both for Simon & Schuster.
      - Contract (Simon & Schuster), 1962 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Setting Copy (Simon & Schuster), 1963 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Subseries I.2: Unpublished Novels and Novellas, circa 1957-1964
    This subseries contains contracts, outlines, drafts, manuscripts, notes, notebooks, and related materials.
    - Subseries I.2.1: Prophets Without Honor, circa 1957-1959
      Prophets Without Honor was to have been Moore's second novel. Knopf purchased the novel based upon an outline submitted by Moore and Laurot, but ultimately rescinded its contact in 1959. Both the contract and the rescindment are in this subseries.
      The subseries also includes outlines, various typescripts, and a portion of the final version (Chapter 7-end, only).
      - Contract and Rescindment (Knopf), 1957, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Note on Revisions (Pamela Moore to Sterling Lord), undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
        It is unclear which version this note pertains to; it may not be in the collection.
      - Outlines, undated; 2 folders (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
      - Outlines and Typescript Pages, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
        Typescript is for pages 1-155, but some pages are missing.
      - Typescript Pages, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
        Typescript is for pages 1-122, but some pages are missing. Heavily annotated working typescript and typescript carbon.
      - Typescript, undated; 4 folders; 696 pages (Box 5, Folder 3-6)
        Heavily annotated typescript and typescript carbon.
      - Typescript, undated; 4 folders; 813 pages (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
        Container cover indicates that this version is the longest version. Contains a few corrections.
      - Clean Typescript (Folder 1, of 3), undated; 1 folders; 540 pages (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Clean Typescript (Folders 2-3, of 3), undated; 2 folders; 540 pages (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
      - Carbon of Clean Typescript, undated; 3 folders; 540 pages (Box 7, Folder 3-5)
      - Final Version (Incomplete) (Folders 1-2, of 3), undated; 2 folders (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
        Typescript contains pages 78-482 (Chapter 7-end), only. Clean typescript.
      - Final Version (Incomplete) (Folder 3, of 3), undated; 1 folders (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Subseries I.2.2: Kathy, circa 1963-1964
      Kathy grew out of Moore's revisions to Prophets Without Honor; the novel was unfinished at the time of Moore's death.
      The early title of this work was Tho' All the World Betrays Thee, and it is also referred to as Kathy on the Rocks and My Sister Kathy. The working contract from Dell for the book (1964) uses the title Debut.
      This subseries includes outlines, notebooks, notes, as well as various carbons, drafts, typescripts, and "rejects."
      There is material related to Kathy in Subseries I.8: Other Notes and Notebooks, and Subseries III.2: Diaries.
      - Contract (Dell), 1964 (Box 8, Folder 2)
        Tentatively titled "Debut"
      - Outline, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Outline and Notes on Eiffel Tower, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Typescript Pages and Notes on Infant Prodigy, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Old Version Notes; Kathy on Long Island; Alex and Ferenc, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Tho' All the World Betrays The--Typescript, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
        Contains pages 1-77 and 133-155.
      - Typescript, undated; 2 folders (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
        Possibly an early version.
      - Typescripts, undated; 8 folders (Box 9, Folder 1-8)
        Several folders of typescripts, carbons, drafts, and "rejects".
      - My Sister Kathy--In Paris; On a Boat; Interview, undated; Typescript (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - My Sister Kathy--Warner and Bing, undated; Typescript (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Current Quotes, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Notebook, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Subseries I.2.3: Other Titles, circa 1957-1964
      This subseries contains materials related to other unfinished novel projects. Most of these, with the exception of "Rosemary", had working titles. It is unclear if any of these were related to Moore's other writing projects.
      This subseries includes outlines, character sketches, synopses, and typescript chapters and pages.
      There is additional material related to some of these projects in Subseries III.2: Diaries.
      - Beauty and the Books, undated; 2 folders (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
        Typescripts for first few chapters, synopsis, notes.
      - The Debut--Outline, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
        Primarily character sketches; this does not appear related to Kathy.
      - The Kowalski Family--Outline, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Mountain of Love, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
        Synopsis, some typescript pages.
      - Northcape, circa 1961 (Box 10, Folder 9)
        Approximately 1" of manuscript and typescript pages, and notes. Moore notes that she is working on a novel with this title in correspondence to E.P. Dutton (1961). Original enclosure is labelled "Northscape: American Search for Myth beyond Reason and Physical Reality"
      - Northcape (Enclosure), circa 1961 (Box 22, Folder 2)
        This is the original enclosure for the Northscape materials, above.
      - Rosemary, undated; 2 folders (Box 10, Folder 10-11)
        This was untitled. Includes approximately 150 typescript pages, maps, and notes. It appears that this and Summer Stage might be the same story.
      - Summer Stage, undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
        Typescripts for the first chapters. It appears that this and Rosemary might be the same story.
  - Subseries I.3: Short Stories, 1945-1962, undated
    This subseries contains drafts and typescripts for several short stories. Many of the stories are untitled, and most are undated.
    - Angela, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Are There Any Wounded?, circa 1962 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Baby Shoes, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
      Title on typescripts is "Battle of Brooklyn Heights." Envelope lists title as "Baby Shoes."
    - Easter Sunday, circa 1953 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      There are other versions of this story in the "Short Stories" folder at the end of this subseries.
    - Gentleman from Virginia, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Greetings from Monaco, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Guilty, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Independence Story, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Ivo, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Maureen, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - The Murder Between Them, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - My Other Lover, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Poor Philippe Story, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Professor Tristan Story, undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Red Shoes, undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
      Unfinished story.
    - She Married a Jew, undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Their Bones Nourish No Sacred Groves, undated (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - What is General Lee Going to Do?, undated (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Pompeiian Red / At Sea / Nina the Arabic Scholar, undated (Box 11, Folder 19)
      Three short pieces; originally housed in one envelope.
    - Short Stories, 1952-1957, undated; 2 folders (Box 11, Folder 20-21)
      This is a set of fiction stories. The set includes "Veteran," "Just an Incident," "The Girl with the Long Hair," "Easter Sunday," "Charm Boy," "The Land," "Haven," "The Lost Gold Mine," "A Full Love," "Bad Actor," and "Motherland." "Bad Actor" is an early story related to Chocolates for Breakfast.
  - Subseries I.4: Poetry, 1950-1952
    This subseries contains one set of poems, written between 1950 and 1952.
    - Poetry, 1950-1952 (Box 11, Folder 22)
      This is a set of poems. The set includes "To the Midnight Caller," "The Night," "Night's Call," "My Evening," "Reason," "A Love of Youth," "Letter to My Fiance," and "La Nuit Vient."
  - Subseries I.5: Plays, undated
    This subseries contains outlines, a few typescript pages, and notes for two undated plays.
    - Be Damned, Eternity, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
      A few typescript pages, outline, and notes.
    - The Shattered Heart, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
      Typescript pages, outlines.
  - Subseries I.6: Articles, 1950s-1960s
    This contains materials related to both published and unpublished articles, and includes typescripts, notes, and clippings of published articles.
    - "A Little Slavic Village in the Heart of Manhattan", undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
      Suggested article for Holiday. See also: "Miscelleneous Works" folder in "Drafts and Fragments" subseries.
    - "Are American Men Afraid of Sex?" Playboy, 1957 February (Box 12, Folder 4)
      Copy of the full issue of Playboy; includes Moore's published article.
    - "Blueprint for the Basic Training of a Wife", undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
      Suggested article for Playboy.
    - Music Hall Article, 1962 April (Box 12, Folder 6)
      Includes typescript, in English, and photocopy of the published version, in French.
    - "Where is Your Husband?", undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
      From envelope labeled, "Articles - Susan"
  - Subseries I.7: Drafts and Fragments, 1942-1978, undated
    This subseries contains a few folders of unorganized manuscript pages, notes, correspondence, and other materials.